本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
Oh... Volken has rebelled,
with Olivia Litlet in tow.
おー　ヴォルケンが反乱をオリビア＝リットレットと共に
Remind me, who is that again?
ほって　誰だったかな
That woman from the Silver Smoke.
白煙号のあの女です
I see.
そうか　どうせハミュッツが殺すだろうが
Hamyuts will probably kill her...
Though... we could lend a hand.
しかし　手は打っておこうか
诸
神&动漫国
剥がれ落ちた夢 澱む幻
Hagare ochita yume yodomu maboroshi
もう この世界を見放した者さえ
Mou kono sekai wo mihanashita
mono sae tsutsumi komu kotoba
包み込む言葉
刹那に消えゆく
Setsuna ni kieyuku
共に囚われの明日を取り戻そう
Tomo ni toraware no ashita wo torimodosou
何もかも失くしても
Nani mo kamo nakushite mo
Saigo no shingi no hi made
最期の審議の日まで　ずっと
Zutto hana no you ni tsuyoku sakihokore
花のように強く咲き誇れ
絶望のオト　拾い集めて
Zetsubou no oto hiroi atsumete
Towa ni kanaderu sutorein ni kaeru
永久に奏でる　ストレインに変える
Wazukana hikari sugaritsuitemo todomaru kara
僅かなヒカリ　すがりついても
留まるから
届けたい　残らず
Todoketai nokorazu
Episode 18
A Propeller, Remembrance, and a Man of Lead
第18话 螺旋桨
与
回忆
和
铅之人
うんー　あのぽっちゃん　やるじゃないかい
That boy's pretty good.
I'm impressed.
さすがだ
I'm just getting started, Bizaku!
まだまだです　ビザクさん
An illusion?
幻か
That which goes does not go.
That which comes does not come.
行くものは行かず　来るものは来ない
The moon is the sun.
月は太陽　小鳥は魚
The birds are the fish.
The living are the dead.
生者は骸　鋼鉄は朧
Steel becomes brittle.
Reality becomes a dream.
現は夢にして　幻想は全ての現なり…
All fantasy becomes reality.
Excellent!
いいぞ　お前たち
Continue performing Magical Deliberation.
そのまま魔術審議を続けろ
オリビア
Olivia...
Fight through it! Endure the pain!
戦え　苦痛に耐えろ
To get back...
…取り戻すために
This is too much!
もうこいつは無理です
This is nothing! Nothing!
まだだよ　まだだ
They'll die if they keep this up!
これ以上続けたら死んでしまう
Die?
死ぬ？
「肉」として生きたって　死んでるも同然だろう
Being dead's no worse than
being alive, for a Meat.
Don't you guys want to be human?
お前らは　人間になりたくないのか
なあ　なりたくないのか
Well? Don't you?!
I-I do.
な、なりたいです
I want to be human, Olivia.
人間に…なりたいです　オリビア
Human...
人間に…
What was that, just now...
今のは…
これでいい　悪くはなかったぞ
That's enough for me.
Not bad.
Bizaku...
ビザクさん
Do you remember what I always said,
when you finished training?
お前に訓練をつけていたとき
必ず　最後に言った言葉だったな
この情況で　口にするのはいささか恥ずかしいが
Though I feel a bit embarrassed saying it to
you again under these circumstances...
You've become strong, Volken.
強くなったな　ヴォルケンよ
フォトナ前代行も　喜んでいるじゃろうって
I'm sure former Acting Director
Fotona would be pleased.
For all you've taught me, thank you.
指導　ありがとうございました
Take it all to heart.
心して　挑めよ
I will!
はい
いたたた…
Ow-ow-ow-ow...
I'll be laid up for two hours now.
これ　あと二時間も動けんな
うん
My pupil has finally surpassed his master.
教え子に敗北する日を味わえるとは　一つ夢が叶ったか
One of my dreams has come true.
How wonderful.
あら　素敵　そのまま夢の世界の住人になっちゃう
Would you like to move to
the world of dreams now?
Let's hurry. This battle has
yet to begin in earnest.
急ぎましょう　今の戦いはまだ前哨戦です
This battle? What are you talking about?
今の戦い？　何のことだ
え？
Huh?
That was no battle.
さっきのあんなのは戦いじゃない
Battles are much dirtier than that.
戦いってのは　もっと汚いもんじゃ
Have you regained your memory, Olivia?
オリビアさん　記憶が？
少しだけが　あたしが相当な悪党だったってことぐらいだが
Somewhat.
I remember that I was pretty nefarious...
That's true.
そうですね
You're not going to say I wasn't?
否定しないのかよ
安心してください
Relax. I know someone more
nefarious than you.
俺は　あなた以上の悪人を知っています
Olivia Litlet...
オリビア＝リットレット
ヴォルケンと白煙号
Volken and the Silver Smoke...
And finally, Renas Fluru...
そしてレナス＝フルール
There's one thing that ties them all together.
この三つを繋ぐ符号はただ一つ
I didn't think he'd still be alive:
まだ生きていたなんてね
ベンド＝ルガー
Vend Ruga.
Ah! It's a rabbit!
あ　うさぎだ
Hamyuts, we don't have time for that.
ハミュッツ　急ぐぞ
This mission is being kept secret from
the other Armed Librarians.
他の武装司書には極秘の任務だ
I'd like to get it over with.
早く終わらせたい
はーい
Okay...
It's been a while.
久しぶりだな　わざわざすまなかった
Sorry to make you come all the way out here.
We've locked a traitor inside this fortress.
あの砦に立て籠もっているのは我らへ反逆者だ
The enemy is a lone woman.
敵は一人の少女
She's a True Man, but she's
attempting to destroy Heaven.
「真人」でありながら天国を滅ぼそうとし
She's taken command of a
considerable number of Mock Men.
多くの「擬人」たちを部下としている
Also,
そして連中が私に対抗するため　強力な兵器を用意した
they've readied a powerful weapon
in order to make their stand against me.
It's regrettable, but we've run out of options.
残念だが　私たちにはもうどうすることもできん
Governor of Paradise, to be perfectly frank,
I'm disappointed by your work.
楽園管理者　正直言って
お前の仕事には失望している
You've failed to guard your intelligence.
情報の管理が不徹底だ
You lack the traits of a True Man.
「真人」の質もよくない
I'm considering relieving you of your duties and
appointing a new Governor of Paradise.
お前を解任し　別の楽園管理者をたてることも
That's enough small talk.
前置きはいいでしょう
Let's get this over with,
so I can play with the bunny.
ちゃちゃっと終らせて　うさちゃんと遊ぶの
I ask that you please take
care of the True Man.
頼みましたよ　あの「真人」を
We shall give the Violet Sinner
「菫の咎人」に　真なる死を
a true death!
Please grant me entrance!
頼もうー
うん
What is this?
なに　これ
鉛でできてるの
It's made of lead?
It's Vend Ruga, the lead golem.
鉛の人形　ベンド＝ルガーだ
What do you want?
用件は？
I've got a proposition for you guys...
あんたらに提案があるのよ
Something that'll benefit us both.
お互いに利益がある話しだから　一応ね
なんだ
What?
Can you guys commit suicide for me?
あんたたち　自殺してくれない？
Vend Ruga!
ベンド＝ルガー
I see. What a pity...
そう　しょうがないな
Any survivors?
生き残りは？
いるわけないでしょ
You're kidding, right?
I'd be lying if I said I weren't
torn as to whether or not
自分で言い出しながら
こうまでする必要があったのか　とは思いますね
all that was necessary.
It was the best course of action.
まっ　賢明でしょう
菫は雑草だもの
Violets are pesky weeds, after all.
The Violet Sinner's thoughts
resonate with all of them.
「菫の咎人」の意志に皆が応え
This grew their followers,
interconnected their minds,
同志が増え　心が繋がれて
最後にはここまで大きくなった
and left them that large.
Opponents like that don't back down easily.
そういうやつらはしぶといわよ
一本でも苗が残っていれば
If you leave even one tiny plant behind,
また野原を菫が覆ってしまう
the violets will just overgrow the garden again.
That's reasoning fit for a candidate
for the next Acting Director.
さすがは　次期館長代行候補
Are you ready to show your true colors?
そろそろ本性現したら？
The Mock Men in the fortress
had no clue how to fight.
砦の「擬人」たちは　ろくに戦い方も知らないで
頼みの綱はベンド＝ルガーだけ
Vend Ruga is their only defense.
However, I don't think them capable
of building such a thing.
でもね
「擬人」たちがあれを作り出せたとは到底思えない
You're the one who created that weapon, right?
どうせいあんたが生み出した兵器ってとこじゃない
You're pretending to be incompetent, planning
an eventual attack on the Armed Librarians.
表向きは無能を装って
いつか　武装司書に対して反乱を起こす
I'm impressed!
素晴らしい
I wasn't worried, having deceived
Fotona completely.
フォトナを騙しきって　安心していたところですが
Call it women's intuition.
女の感てやつよ
ベンド＝ルガーはもとは人間なのです
Vend Ruga was, at one time, human.
屈強な男を寄せ集め　その記憶を消し
I gathered many men of physical strength
and erased their memories.
魔術で動くための動力装置を　脳に埋め込んだ
A device was planted into their brains,
to make them move via magic.
Golems created from human parts...
人間という素材を使った人形
They all share a single mind.
彼らは全員が一つの思考を共有しています
Give an order to one of them,
and they all receive it.
一人に命令をすれば全てのものに行き渡る
どれだけ距離が離れていようと　関係ない
Your distance from them is irrelevant.
It was meant to be our main weapon
in the war against the Armed Librarians.
対武装司書の主力兵器となるべき存在でした
しかし先ほど最後の二体があなたに破壊された
However, you just destroyed the final two units!
They did put up a good fight...
なかなか手強かったわよ
But no more than something
to kill some free time with.
暇つぶし程度にしかならなかったけど
Indeed. In that state,
Vend Ruga stood no chance against you.
えー　ベンド＝ルガーがあれではあなた方に適うはずがない
It took us ten years to develop them.
あれの開発には十年かかりましたからね
Oh?
えー
We don't have to give up on
rebelling against you altogether.
反乱などもう諦めざるをえないでしょう
It'll just be another ten years.
次の知恵を結実させるにはまた10年
I'll wait.
待ってあげる
I'll wait ten years.
10年　待ってあげる
In return, you have to let
me have my fun, okay?
その代わり私を　楽しませてくれるわね
"Vend Ruga is alive"?
ベンド＝ルガーが生きている
Yes. They say a lead golem is
fighting the Church,
あー　クラー自治区の内戦地帯で
鉛の人形が神溺教団に刃向かっていると
in the area of the Kra District civil war.
Hmm...
ベンド＝ルガーに残る「菫の咎人」の記憶
The Violet Sinner's memories
were left in Vend Ruga.
Those thoughts are being
propagated among them.
彼らは思考を伝達する　一体でも残れば
As long as one unit remains,
the Violet Sinner will never have a true death.
「菫の咎人」に真なる死は訪れない
This ends it for real, huh?
これで　本当に終わりね
"Vend Ruga is alive."
ベンド＝ルガーは生きている
"He is living inside Olivia Litlet."
オリビア＝リットレットの心の中に生きている
I killed them in the fortress.
砦で殺して　内戦地帯で殺した
I killed them in the area of the civil war.
I thought I had eradicated
their mind, once and for all.
彼の意思を継ぐはずであろう存在も殺した
Over and over again, I killed them.
何度も何度も殺した
なのに
And yet...
Ah! Damned cockroach!
あー　ゴキブリ
What's with this piece of junk?
なんだよ　このポンコツ
Since I stole it from Bantorra,
バントーラから盗み出したものですが
I thought taking a new plane would
be too much imposition.
新型を盗めば　迷惑がかかりすぎるので
Are you stupid?
アホか
お前は武装司書と戦うつもりなんだろうか
Aren't you trying to fight
the Armed Librarians?
I'm fighting Hamyuts!
Not the Armed Librarians!
戦う相手はハミュッツです
武装司書ではない
聞こえますか　ヴォルケン＝マクマーニ
Do you copy, Volken Macmani?
ミレポック
Milepoc...
There's no time to waste. I'll make this quick.
無駄話をしている時間はありません
用件を手短に伝えます
O- Okay.
あ、あー
まずひとつ　代行の飛行艇にエンジントラブルがありました
First off, the Acting Director's plane
had some engine trouble.
She won't catch up to you for some time.
あなたに追いつくのはまだ先になるでしょう
Also...
そして　代行不在のまま非公式に会議を行いました
We held an unofficial meeting during
the Acting Director's absence.
Most of the Armed Librarians took your side.
そこで　武装司書のほとんどがあなたを支持した
本当か？
Really?
Yes. I will give you the
details when necessary.
え　これからは随時　あなたに情報を伝えていきます
I see. Thank you for telling me this, Milepoc.
そうか
教えてくれてありがとう　ミレポック
I'm just letting you know their decision!
私は決定を伝えただけです
That is all.
それでは
Guys...
みんな
What happened?
どうしたよ？
武装司書が俺たちに見方をしてくれています
The Armed Librarians are supporting us.
We're not alone!
俺たちは孤独じゃない
Huh?
は？
I did things that could be seen as crimes,
俺は傍目には罪とも取れる行動を重ねた
but they saw through to my true intentions,
だが　その真意を汲み　信頼してくれる仲間がいる
and they stand by my side.
Are you serious?
本当か？
Huh?
It's painfully obvious how naïve you are.
あんたがあまっちゃんなのはいやほど分かってるわね
そんなに簡単に他人を信用していいのか？
Should you really be so
quick to trust others?
It's something that someone as nefarious
as you couldn't understand.
あなたのような悪党には　到底理解できないことです
あー　そうかい？
Oh, right.
うん　ここはどこだ
Huh? Where are we?
The Kra District.
クラー自治区です
戦争は終わったのか
The war's over?
Yes. The independence army won.
え　独立軍が勝利して　今休戦中ですが
They then ceased fire.
ヴォルケン　降ろせ
Volken, land here.
I was here once!
私はここにいたんだ
Here with Vend Ruga!
ここで　ベンド＝ルガーと
It seems he believed me.
信じてようです
I see.
そうか
Funeral bells...
弔いの鐘
ビザクさんの死を泣いている
They're ringing for Bizaku.
I heard it from Dulltom.
ダルトムから連絡があった
傷口は鋭い刃物で切り裂かれていたと
He said he was sliced up
with a very sharp blade.
Also, it was...
それは…
Volken's Flying Blades.
ヴォルケンの舞い剣
あいつ　信じられない
I don't believe him...
How could he kill his master?
師匠を手にかけるなんて
Are we sure he killed him?
本当に　彼が殺したのでしょうか？
I just heard Volken Macmani's
thoughts a few minutes ago.
私はヴォルケン＝マクマーニの思考をじかで聞きました
He didn't sound like he had just
killed his master at all.
とても恩師を殺した直後とは思えない
Then who the hell killed Bizaku?!
じゃ　ビザクさんは誰が殺したって言うんだ
If we wait until Bizaku becomes a book...
それはビザクさんが「本」になるまで待てば
It's true. Volken hadn't changed at all.
ヴォルケンは確かに以前とは変わらなかった
Honest and pure to a fault...
純粋で　愚直で
But sometimes, being too pure and strong
of will can lead one down the wrong path.
だが　純粋すぎる強い意志は
時に人を間違った方へと突き動かす
帰ってきたよ　ベンド=ルガー
I'm back, Vend Ruga.
Look. He's been waiting for a long time.
おい　こいつかなり持ってるぜ
そうそう　知ってるか　鉛の人形
Oh, yeah. Do you know about the lead golem?
Yeah, looks like Ramba got taken before, too.
うん　この間もランバーが攫われたらしいぜ
Man, messed him up good...
えー　湿気てあがんな
This'll satisfy my hunger a little bit...
これっぽちじゃ　腹の足しに…
Actually, it won't.
あー　腹の足しになりゃしない
Give it to me!
あたしに寄越しな
Let me go!
放せ
One child captured!
子供一人捕獲
That's right... Vend Ruga saved me here.
そうだ　私はここでベンド＝ルガーに助けられた
But, afterwards...
でも　その後は…
Olivia!
オリビアさん　追いつかれる可能性は少ないとはいえ
Though it's unlikely she'll catch up to us,
代行は脅威です
the Acting Director is dangerous!
それほどには…
We don't have time to...
少し黙ってろ
Shut your mouth!
I'm on the verge of getting my
memory back, so leave me alone!
思い出せそうなんだから　一人にしてくれ
You've got fifteen minutes.
15分ですよ
「肉」の分際で偉そうに
A Meat acting all high and mighty...
That damned sorcerer's just
being charmed by the Meat.
あの魔法使いめ　「肉」の色香に騙されやがて
The Church believes Charlot's
teleportation to be important.
シャーロットの使う空間転移の魔術は　教団にとって重要だ
We're really in no position to argue.
俺たちには口答えはできんさ
I love you, Master Charlot.
シャーロット様　大好き
Olivia...
オリビア
Hmm?
うん
What are you using Ylucklucu
and the Meats for?
ユックユックと「肉」を使ってなにをしてるんで？
I don't like it when you ask me such things.
そんなこと聞くシャーロット様も嫌い
Olivia...
オリビア　たとえ嘘でも　嫌いなどと言わずにいてほしい
Please don't say you don't like me,
even if you're just kidding.
You're everything to me.
お前は私の全て
Your delicate shoulders,
この華奢な肩　滑らかな肌
your soft skin...
また死んだか
Another one dead?
If you continue Magical Deliberation,
ここまま魔術審議を続けては
it'll only lead to more of our comrades dying!
仲間たちの犠牲は増えるばかりです
Who cares?
それがどうした
We're trying to get back...
…を取り戻すためなら
He died for you!
あなたのために彼は死んだ
Doesn't that sadden you?!
悲しくはないのですか
For a Meat, you sure talk a lot.
よく喋る「肉」だな
Why should I feel sad? I'm a Meat, too.
悲しいはずはないだろう
あたしも「肉」だ　感情なんてない
I don't feel anything.
Why must you lie?
どうして嘘をつくのですか
本心だよ
It's the truth!
Olivia!
オリビア
本心だよ
It's the truth.
うん　どんだ女だよ　あたしは
I'm one crazy woman...
Sacrificing those who adore me
for my own selfish desires.
慕ってきたやつらを　ことごとく自分の欲望のために
What on earth was I trying to recover
that would drive me to do such things?
そこまでして　私は
何を取り戻したかったって言うんだ
Olivia.
オリビア
レナス
Renas? Is that you, Renas Fluru?
レナス＝フルールか
You're still there?
お前はまだ…
You still haven't realized the
most important thing.
あなたは一番大事なことに気付いていない
だから目的も思い出せない
That's why you can't remember
what you were after.
Shut your lousy mouth!
うるさい　黙れ
すぐさばけしてやる　お前なんて
I'll erase you in a heartbeat!
Remember, Olivia.
思いだして　オリビア
あなたは心から冷酷な人間ではない
Deep down inside, you're not so heartless.
思い出して
Remember.
Volken Macmani, do you copy?
ヴォルケン＝マクマーニ　聞こえますか
Milepoc!
ミレポック
What is it? Is the Acting Director
up to something?
どうした　代行に何か動きがあったか
いえ　情況はどうかと
No... I just wanted to check on you.
You were worried about me?
心配してくれたのか？
Th-That's not why.
そういうわけでは…
ラスコールの絵本を読んでくれたんだな
You read Lascall's picture book, didn't you?
What? You're the one who left me that book?
あの本はあなたが置いていったの？
どういうつもり？
Why would you do that?
I went after Lascall because of that book!
私は真に受けてラスコールを追ったのよ
あっ　ラスコールを？
Went after Lascall?
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
All I ever did was cause you trouble.
お前には迷惑かけてばかりだ
I can't believe you'd go after
Lascall because of me...
俺なんかのために　ラスコールを
And drink from Argax because of me.
そして　アーガックスまで
Volken Macmani?
ヴォルケン＝マクマーニ
ミレポック
Milepoc.
え？
Huh?
I'm sorry for everything.
いつもすまない
Milepoc.
ミレポック
What?
なに？
I'm sorry for everything.
いつもすまない
ヴォルケン
Volken...
Run!
逃げて　逃げて　ヴォルケン
Huh?
Run, Volken!
Don't stay there!
そこにいてはだめ　代行が…
The Acting Director's...
What's going on?
どうした？
あ…
Milepoc!
ミレポック　どうしたんだ　ミレポック
What is it, Milepoc?!
What is Hamyuts going to do?
ハミュッツが何を…
Olivia!
オリビアさん　ハミュッツ＝メセタが…
Hamyuts Meseta, she's...
Before Vend Ruga, my main dish...
メインディッシュのベンド＝ルガーの前に
Volken, Olivia, since you two are together...
ヴォルケン　オリビア
あんたたち二人がかりなら…
前から後ろからきまくっちゃって
Come out, come out, wherever you are.
Tobu hane yume toraete
Tobu mane yami oyoideru
Aoku kanashii sora ni kotae kiite miyou
Shimaru tobira tataita (tsuyoku)
Nukedashite saigo no aisatsu
Dare wo sagashi tsuzuketa no to
Koe wo ubawareru dake de wakaranai
Oreta ai no seide
Nanimokamo nakushita ima
Tenshi wa mou konai
Dominant Space
A young man has lost everything,
全てを失い
A Fool,
A young man has lost everything,
and he has now become free.
全てから解き放たれた青年
But he's gained a witch of reminiscence.
手に入れたのは　追想の魔女
A Fool, a Void,
But he's gained a witch of reminiscence.
He's embraced everything he ever wanted.
望む全てを抱き締めた
A Fool, a Void, and a Dancing Golem
He's embraced everything he ever wanted.
傻瓜与虚空和舞蹈的人偶
A Fool, a Void, and a Dancing Golem